<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: job descriptions | Becoming Medium]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.becomingmedium.com/blog/categories/job-descriptions/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.becomingmedium.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-16T22:09:15-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.becomingmedium.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Wes Bailey]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Flexible Framework for Leveling Software Engineers]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.becomingmedium.com/blog/2013/09/24/career-levels/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-24T11:43:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.becomingmedium.com/blog/2013/09/24/career-levels</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>The Problem</h3>

<p>Defining a Senior Software Engineer seems to be a pretty difficult task for our industry.  Managing
expectations around this definition is also really difficult and causes strife in organizations that
are trying to grow and retain talent.  The current methodology is to create a &ldquo;<em>Job Description</em>&rdquo;
which focuses on &ldquo;<em>responsibilities</em>&rdquo; and &ldquo;<em>requirements</em>&rdquo; by listing the work skills, technical
requirements and years of experience required for the position.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Like everyone else, I used this approach for a while until I ran into problems.  I started looking
for a framework that I could use to scale an organization in both talent evaluation and career
development.  I wanted answers to questions like:</p>

<ul>
<li>How do you differentiate between a Software Engineer and a Senior Software Engineer?</li>
<li>Is seniority based on years of experience or based on technical capability?</li>
<li>How do you promote and fairly compensate engineers who use different languages and tools?</li>
<li>How can you evaluate new talent consistently and compare them with the current members on your
team?</li>
<li>Where do the required years of experience come from and are they just an artificial crutch
justification?</li>
<li>How do you mentor engineers in their career and so that they can grow and learn?</li>
</ul>


<p>There are more questions to be answered but this is a good starter set.  Naturally, I searched the web for
answers.  It turned up a couple of somewhat useful threads on
<a href="http://programmers.stackexchange.com/questions/14914/whats-the-difference-between-entry-level-jr-sr-developers">programmers.stackexchange</a>
and on
<a href="http://www.quora.com/When-does-a-software-developer-become-a-senior-software-developer">Quora</a> and
while they left me admiring the technical complexity of some of the answers, there was still
something missing.</p>

<p>Not finding what I wanted online, I talked with a few peers in my network. Turns out they use the
&ldquo;<em>Job Description</em>&rdquo; method and they agree it is a failed approach.  Since my search turned empty I
instead spent a lot of time thinking on the topic and came up with a framework that provides
guidelines for making the decisions around the questions above.</p>

<h3>A New Approach</h3>

<p>It is important to understand that the definition is actually for many levels than just the Senior
Software Engineer.  There are some who argue for a <a href="http://link_to_brian_cantrells_talk">&ldquo;<em>flat</em>&rdquo; organization</a>,
but I&rsquo;ll address that myth in another blog post.  We should ensure that our level definitions make
it easy to answer the questions we posited previously.  They should also help us lay the foundation
for a career progression that is possible within the company helping us retain talented people.</p>

<p>The challenge I set for myself which really helped provide a different frame of reference was to
answer the following question:</p>

<blockquote><p>If you could describe what an engineer at this level will do using only word, what would it be?</p></blockquote>

<p>A single word is succint, descriptive and most importantly memorable.  It will be easy for your
teams to digest and in discussions leverage the simplicity.  A single word is only useful if we can
provide context so the next step in the framework is to provide a single sentence description of the
level.</p>

<blockquote><p>Summarize what the person at this level will be doing in a single sentence incorporating the
single word definition from the previous step</p></blockquote>

<p>Building upon context we can switch to defining the major areas of focus the role should have at
this level:</p>

<blockquote><p>Define 3 to 4 technically agnostic areas of focus that provide guidance for a person performing at
this level.</p></blockquote>

<p>It is important with the last step of the approach to not get caught up in the details of the
technical requirements.  Doing so prevents you from having an overall framework and leads to the
dreaded <em>Job Description</em> model that we previously stated doesn&rsquo;t help solve any problems.</p>

<h3>An Example</h3>

<p>Let&rsquo;s walk through how I applied the model to engineering at <a href="http://www.modcloth.com">ModCloth</a>
where we have 3 levels in the software development position:</p>

<ul>
<li>Associate Software Engineer</li>
<li>Software Engineer</li>
<li>Senior Software Engineer</li>
</ul>


<p>Of course we have other roles on the team as well such as test and platform engineers and I am sure
you do on your team&rsquo;s as well, but I&rsquo;ll leave them out for brevity.</p>

<h3>Associate Software Engineer</h3>

<p>This level is reserved for beginners, someone who is fresh out of school or making a career change.
We don&rsquo;t expect them to have a lot of experience and it is easy to envision them spending their
first year <em>learning</em> about the languages used and best practices of their team.  Applying the model
we have the following:</p>

<h4>Description</h4>

<p><em>Learning</em></p>

<h4>Context</h4>

<p><em>At the Associate level you are learning skills and developing competence.</em></p>

<h4>Areas of Focus</h4>

<ul>
<li><em>Develop a basic understanding of the languages and tools used by the team.</em></li>
<li><em>Gain exposure to software development best practices such as TDD, debugging, documentation, etc.</em></li>
<li><em>Learn good communication skills to be used with your teammates.</em></li>
</ul>


<h3>Software Engineer</h3>

<p>At this level the engineer understands the basics of the areas of focus from the previous level.
The distinction is they are now <em>applying</em> their basic skills instead of learning what they are and
requiring supervision.  Of course we are always learning but the difference is the person can now be
trusted to apply their newly acquired skills independently.</p>

<h4>Description</h4>

<p><em>Practicing</em></p>

<h4>Context</h4>

<p><em>At the Software level you are applying your skills and developing expertise</em></p>

<h4>Areas of Focus</h4>

<ul>
<li><em>Leverage best practices to write and continually improve the code base.</em></li>
<li><em>Develop mastery in the tools, languages and frameworks used by the team.</em></li>
<li><em>Begin practicing and learning how to teach/mentor less experienced teammates.</em></li>
</ul>


<h3>Senior Software Engineer</h3>

<p>This level of engineer is the crux of any successful engineering team.  They are able to go beyond
just using tools and techniques and now recommend what the team should do and how to go about it.
They have accomplished a technical maturity that allows them to solve complex problems and begin to
take an ownership position on the code and systems they haven&rsquo;t developed.</p>

<h4>Description</h4>

<p><em>Mentoring</em></p>

<h4>Context</h4>

<p><em>At the Senior level you are mentoring your teammates and sharing expertise</em></p>

<h4>Level Areas of Focus</h4>

<ul>
<li><em>Develop the necessary best practices to work with and write a great code base.</em></li>
<li><em>Help evaluate and select the tools, languages and frameworks used by the team.</em></li>
<li><em>On board and mentor new members of the team ensuring their success.</em></li>
<li><em>Begin to take an ownership position on code and systems developed by others</em></li>
</ul>


<h3>Summary</h3>

<p>We have covered a model framework for defining the different levels of any role within an
organization.  The benefits of the model are that it can be applied to role in the orginization and
is scalable.   A simple moniker for remembering the model follows below:</p>

<blockquote><p>Description &ndash;> Context &ndash;> Areas of Focus</p></blockquote>

<p>Let&rsquo;s revisit how the example application of the model answers the questions posed at the beginning
of this blog.  By providing simple and flexible areas of focus it helps evaluate and contrast the
different levels in the defined role easily.  It is technology and years of experience agnostic
instead judging engineers on their ability to go from individual to more team focused contributors.
It also makes learning and mentoring a key component of how the team will judge it&rsquo;s success.</p>

<p>The one question is doesn&rsquo;t answer is where the years of experience numbers come from?  Honestly, I
have no idea and nor do I need to care anymore when writing a new job description!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
