<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: professional development | Becoming Medium]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.becomingmedium.com/blog/categories/professional-development/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.becomingmedium.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-11T10:52:27-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.becomingmedium.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Wes Bailey]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Avoiding Paper Tigers, Leeches and Space Cadets]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.becomingmedium.com/blog/2013/10/28/avoiding-paper-tigers-and-leaches/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-28T10:53:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.becomingmedium.com/blog/2013/10/28/avoiding-paper-tigers-and-leaches</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Recruiting</h3>

<p>One of my favorite aspects about my job is recruiting.  I absolutely love it!  It&rsquo;s true.
Recruiting allows me to meet a lot of engineers and talk shop.  You  get to learn all about their
backgrounds, interests, companies they have worked for and amazing projects they have worked on.  If
you are lucky you also have an amazing technical conversation at some point that leaves everyone
impressed.  What is not to love?</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Well, I don&rsquo;t love disappointing my team with a candidate.  We have all been there either as a
hiring manager or a member of the team.  The team is totally pumped and excited to meet whiz bang
candidate and interview them.  However, after the candidate gets past the introductory phase
everyone on the interview panel realizes they have been duped.  The candidate turns out to be a
complete dud.  We are left to wonder how they made it through the screening process and got this
far?  It sucks and neither the team or the candidate is happy about it.</p>

<p>In this post I am going to introduce you to candidates that I have dubbed <em>paper tigers</em>, <em>leeches</em>
and <em>space cadets</em>.  These are the candidate types who in my experience you want to avoid like the
plague.  The problem is how do we identify them and discover them early on in the process?  What
characteristics do they have in common with great candidates that make them hard to distinguish?
What questions can we ask them during a phone screen to ferret them out?</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t have prescriptive answers for all of these questions to be honest.  I think by sharing my
experience and raising some valid points, you might be able to avoid candidates like this in the
future providing a better search experience for your team and the prospective candidates.</p>

<h3>Screening 101</h3>

<p>How many times have you read a candidate&rsquo;s resume and thought to yourself how amazing this person is
and what a great candidate they would make for your open position?  Reviewing resumes and screening
prospective candidates is not an easy thing to do.  Resumes come in all forms and flavors making it
difficult sometimes to read whether a candidate has the relevant experience necessary for the job.
A few things that I have noticed that help in the process include the following:</p>

<ul>
<li><em>Reject any candidate that doesn&rsquo;t write a personalized cover letter</em> - It doesn&rsquo;t take that much
effort to explain why you are interested and why your experience is right for the job then don&rsquo;t
bother.</li>
<li><em>Favor resumes that tell a story and really emphasize what the candidate is interested in and
passionate about</em> - If people are doing it just for the money they won&rsquo;t make great members of
your team.</li>
<li><em>Resumes that illustrate how they used their skills are better than ones that just list everything
they have ever used</em> - I dislike people who just mind numblingly list programming languages they
have used.  You can&rsquo;t tell if they have only played with the language or whether they used it
professionally</li>
<li><em>Forget resumes that have more than one grammatical error or spelling mistakes right away</em> - I
know this is tough for folks where English isn&rsquo;t their first language.  There are so many tools
now that to me it reflects effort more than language difficulty.</li>
<li><em>Weed out resumes that don&rsquo;t contain the relevant experience or work history in them because
stretch candidates rarely work in practice</em> - This is just a no brainer to me.</li>
<li><em>A pet peeve of mine is resumes that are sent as Word docs instead of PDFs especially for
technology positions</em> - Send a PDF so I don&rsquo;t have to worry about which version of Word I have
installed or how crappy the doc gets displayed when converted in Google Docs.</li>
</ul>


<p>Of course there are more tips for screening but this isn&rsquo;t meant to be a comprehensive breakdown of
how to filter through resumes.  Years ago, Joel Spolsky wrote a nice
<a href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/SortingResumes.html">piece</a> on the subject so you can read
that for reference.</p>

<h3>Paper Tigers</h3>

<p>Like the name I have given them implies, the best way to describe people who fall into this
category is that they look fantastic on paper but completely underwhelm when interviewed in person.
They either totally lack on the technical side or something else comes up where they don&rsquo;t impress.
Not being to totally put my finger on this person here are a few characteristics that I have noticed
about them.  Here are what you will immediately see when you read their resume:</p>

<ul>
<li>Their resume is easy to read and really well organized making it clear who they worked for and
what they worked on.</li>
<li>The companies they have worked for are well known for their products or development teams and it
seems they made great contributions to either or both.</li>
<li>The person has a solid educational background with degrees from well known schools and programs.</li>
<li>The projects they list are relevant and have a high correlation to the position they are applying
for.</li>
<li>They perfectly meet all of the requirements for the level of experience for the position.</li>
</ul>


<p>This all sounds great so where does it go awry?  Well this is what I have found to be true from
<em>paper tigers</em> when I phone screen or interview them in person:</p>

<ul>
<li>They tailored their resume to perfectly fit the job description however they neither have the
skills or the experience required.</li>
<li>If they are from an agency you find the recruiter just &ldquo;<em>resume stuffed</em>&rdquo; and the person who you
are speaking with isn&rsquo;t really the person they presented on paper.</li>
<li>They listed they are qualified in too many technologies, languages and frameworks when you drill
you confirm your notion that no one person can be an expert in everything they listed.</li>
<li>When you dig into their experience, you find they are part of a larger team and didn&rsquo;t have the
hands on experience and had actual little involvement in the project or technology</li>
<li>Another quality is listing items they haven&rsquo;t worked with in production but it shows up on their
resume as if they have.</li>
<li>They lie about the amount of experience and later it comes out that they have much less than they
claimed because they claim the length of the entire project as their own vs their actual
involvement in it.</li>
<li>They did the project on their own time and have never done it professionally but count it as real
experience on their resume.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Leeches</h3>

<p>The next category I have dubbed <em>Leeches</em> because like a leach, they survive off of the work of
others.  In their resumes they take credit for others but instead of being caught in the phone
screen, they pull it off and might not be exposed until you hire them.  When they join your team
they drain it just like a parasite which is bad for the team&rsquo;s productivity, chemistry and moral.
Some of the characteristics of this type of candidate include most everything from the <em>paper tiger</em>
and additionally:</p>

<ul>
<li>They led or worked with an offshore team or remote team in another location.</li>
<li>They will claim to have setup or built a team but in reality they had no part in the growth at
all.</li>
<li>They indicate they selected a technology or vendor but then never worked with them or were part of
the implementation.</li>
<li>There was strong technical leadership on the team that they are trying to take credit for as their
work and actions and involvement.</li>
<li>You find out through references that this person isn&rsquo;t in the top half of people that person has
worked with.</li>
<li>They know just enough to be dangerous but don&rsquo;t have the full experience and rely on their
teammates to actually do the work.</li>
<li>Beware the phantom and exaggerated titles from smaller companies that imply leadership and
experience but when you drill in they don&rsquo;t have it.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Space Cadet</h3>

<p>This is a more recent category of candidate for me.  Several times in my career I have come across a
bright individual and think the person could fill in more than one role on the team.  The problem
with this person is they really don&rsquo;t know what they want to do with their careers.  Sometimes some
simple coaching can really benefit this type of candidate, but other times you are just dealing with
a person who really doesn&rsquo;t know what they want to do.  This person I call a <em>space cadet</em> because
they have no clue and if you bring them on to your team, they will ultimately blow it up like a
failed rocket launch through their ambivalent actions.</p>

<p>How do you tell if you are talking to a <em>space cadet</em>?  Here are a few things that might help you
discern them from good candidates:</p>

<ul>
<li>They work at a very large company where they can kind of drift and hide from real responsibility
or success.</li>
<li>The person has worked at their present company for a rather long time.</li>
<li>They have found a unique position at their current company that doesn&rsquo;t really apply to your
company.</li>
<li>The person is unsure whether they want to be a manager or a technical lead.  The main reason they
are unsure is because they don&rsquo;t really understand the difference between the roles.</li>
<li>The candidate is usually a really smart and well educated person but you just have a hunch they
haven&rsquo;t fully applied themselves like other candidates with similar backgrounds have.</li>
<li>They just totally have no freaking idea what they really want to do or how to effectively use
their talents.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Discovery Techniques</h3>

<p>I don&rsquo;t have any powerful insights here except to take the time to really get to know the candidate.
One technique I use is to ask open ended questions and see where the candidate goes with their
response.  You&rsquo;ll know if they are bluffing or really qualified as you ask more questions that
involve them sharing the depth of their knowledge.</p>

<p>One example when it comes to roles is:</p>

<blockquote><p>How do you define good software architecture?</p></blockquote>

<p>Totally open ended and doesn&rsquo;t give anything away.  The answer can go anywhere from discussing
<em>Design Patterns</em> to <a href="http://www.sandimetz.com">Sandi Metz Rules</a></p>

<p>As an example one of my favorite ruby questions was simply:</p>

<blockquote><p>What is the difference between an array and a hash in ruby?</p></blockquote>

<p>If you wind up talking about indexes and the conversation stops there the candidate is pretty
junior.  If they take it all the way to the C code in the MRI discussing the b-tree search for the
hash then you know they&rsquo;ve been there and done that!</p>

<p>Another trick I have used to suss people like this out is to ask the same or a related question
again either during the interview, or for the next round of the interview process.  If candidates
can&rsquo;t keep their stories and answers straight there is pretty high likelihood of them being a <em>paper
tiger</em> or a <em>leach</em>.</p>

<p>Let me know what your experience has been!  Have you interviewed these types of candidates and what
techniques did you use to separate them out from the good candidates you wanted to move ahead with?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Flexible Framework for Leveling Software Engineers]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.becomingmedium.com/blog/2013/09/24/career-levels/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-24T11:43:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.becomingmedium.com/blog/2013/09/24/career-levels</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>The Problem</h3>

<p>Defining a Senior Software Engineer seems to be a pretty difficult task for our industry.  Managing
expectations around this definition is also really difficult and causes strife in organizations that
are trying to grow and retain talent.  The current methodology is to create a &ldquo;<em>Job Description</em>&rdquo;
which focuses on &ldquo;<em>responsibilities</em>&rdquo; and &ldquo;<em>requirements</em>&rdquo; by listing the work skills, technical
requirements and years of experience required for the position.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Like everyone else, I used this approach for a while until I ran into problems.  I started looking
for a framework that I could use to scale an organization in both talent evaluation and career
development.  I wanted answers to questions like:</p>

<ul>
<li>How do you differentiate between a Software Engineer and a Senior Software Engineer?</li>
<li>Is seniority based on years of experience or based on technical capability?</li>
<li>How do you promote and fairly compensate engineers who use different languages and tools?</li>
<li>How can you evaluate new talent consistently and compare them with the current members on your
team?</li>
<li>Where do the required years of experience come from and are they just an artificial crutch
justification?</li>
<li>How do you mentor engineers in their career so that they can grow and learn?</li>
</ul>


<p>There are more questions to be answered but this is a good starter set.  Naturally, I searched the web for
answers.  It turned up a couple of somewhat useful threads on
<a href="http://programmers.stackexchange.com/questions/14914/whats-the-difference-between-entry-level-jr-sr-developers">programmers.stackexchange</a>
and on
<a href="http://www.quora.com/When-does-a-software-developer-become-a-senior-software-developer">Quora</a> and
while they left me admiring the technical complexity of some of the answers, there was still
something missing.</p>

<p>Not finding what I wanted online, I talked with a few peers in my network. Turns out they use the
&ldquo;<em>Job Description</em>&rdquo; method and they agree it is a failed approach.  Since my search turned empty I
instead spent a lot of time thinking on the topic and came up with a framework that provides
guidelines for making the decisions around the questions above.</p>

<h3>A New Approach</h3>

<p>It is important to understand that the definition is actually for many levels than just the Senior
Software Engineer.  There are some who argue for a <a href="http://http://www.slideshare.net/bcantrill/surge2013">flat organization</a>,
but I&rsquo;ll address that myth in another blog post.  We should ensure that our level definitions make
it easy to answer the questions we posited previously.  They should also help us lay the foundation
for a career progression that is possible within the company helping us retain talented people.</p>

<p>The challenge I set for myself which really helped provide a different frame of reference was to
answer the following question:</p>

<blockquote><p>If you could describe what an engineer at this level will do using only word, what would it be?</p></blockquote>

<p>A single word is succinct, descriptive and most importantly memorable.  It will be easy for your
teams to digest and in discussions leverage the simplicity.  A single word is only useful if we can
provide context so the next step in the framework is to provide a single sentence description of the
level.</p>

<blockquote><p>Summarize what the person at this level will be doing in a single sentence incorporating the
single word definition from the previous step</p></blockquote>

<p>Building upon context we can switch to defining the major areas of focus the role should have at
this level:</p>

<blockquote><p>Define 3 to 4 technically agnostic areas of focus that provide guidance for a person performing at
this level.</p></blockquote>

<p>It is important with the last step of the approach to not get caught up in the details of the
technical requirements.  Doing so prevents you from having an overall framework and leads to the
dreaded <em>Job Description</em> model that we previously stated doesn&rsquo;t help solve any problems.</p>

<h3>An Example</h3>

<p>Let&rsquo;s walk through how I applied the model to engineering at <a href="http://www.modcloth.com">ModCloth</a>
where we have 3 levels in the software development position:</p>

<ul>
<li>Associate Software Engineer</li>
<li>Software Engineer</li>
<li>Senior Software Engineer</li>
</ul>


<p>Of course we have other roles on the team as well such as test and platform engineers and I am sure
you do on your team&rsquo;s as well, but I&rsquo;ll leave them out for brevity.</p>

<h3>Associate Software Engineer</h3>

<p>This level is reserved for beginners, someone who is fresh out of school or making a career change.
We don&rsquo;t expect them to have a lot of experience and it is easy to envision them spending their
first year <em>learning</em> about the languages used and best practices of their team.  Applying the model
we have the following:</p>

<h4>Description</h4>

<p><em>Learning</em></p>

<h4>Context</h4>

<p><em>At the Associate level you are learning skills and developing competence.</em></p>

<h4>Areas of Focus</h4>

<ul>
<li><em>Develop a basic understanding of the languages and tools used by the team.</em></li>
<li><em>Gain exposure to software development best practices such as TDD, debugging, documentation, etc.</em></li>
<li><em>Learn good communication skills to be used with your teammates.</em></li>
</ul>


<h3>Software Engineer</h3>

<p>At this level the engineer understands the basics of the areas of focus from the previous level.
The distinction is they are now <em>applying</em> their basic skills instead of learning what they are and
requiring supervision.  Of course we are always learning but the difference is the person can now be
trusted to apply their newly acquired skills independently.</p>

<h4>Description</h4>

<p><em>Practicing</em></p>

<h4>Context</h4>

<p><em>At the Software level you are applying your skills and developing expertise</em></p>

<h4>Areas of Focus</h4>

<ul>
<li><em>Leverage best practices to write and continually improve the code base.</em></li>
<li><em>Develop mastery in the tools, languages and frameworks used by the team.</em></li>
<li><em>Begin practicing and learning how to teach/mentor less experienced teammates.</em></li>
</ul>


<h3>Senior Software Engineer</h3>

<p>This level of engineer is the crux of any successful engineering team.  They are able to go beyond
just using tools and techniques and now recommend what the team should do and how to go about it.
They have accomplished a technical maturity that allows them to solve complex problems and begin to
take an ownership position on the code and systems they haven&rsquo;t developed.</p>

<h4>Description</h4>

<p><em>Mentoring</em></p>

<h4>Context</h4>

<p><em>At the Senior level you are mentoring your teammates and sharing expertise</em></p>

<h4>Level Areas of Focus</h4>

<ul>
<li><em>Develop the necessary best practices to work with and write a great code base.</em></li>
<li><em>Help evaluate and select the tools, languages and frameworks used by the team.</em></li>
<li><em>On board and mentor new members of the team ensuring their success.</em></li>
<li><em>Begin to take an ownership position on code and systems developed by others</em></li>
</ul>


<h3>Summary</h3>

<p>We have covered a model framework for defining the different levels of any role within an
organization.  The benefits of the model are that it can be applied to any role in the organization
and is scalable.   A simple moniker for remembering the model follows below:</p>

<blockquote><p>Description -> Context -> Areas of Focus</p></blockquote>

<p>Let&rsquo;s revisit how the example application of the model answers the questions posed at the beginning
of this blog.  By providing simple and flexible areas of focus it helps evaluate and contrast the
different levels in the defined role easily.  It is technology and years of experience agnostic
instead judging engineers on their ability to go from individual to more team focused contributors.
It also makes learning and mentoring a key component of how the team will judge it&rsquo;s success.</p>

<p>The one question it doesn&rsquo;t answer is where the years of experience numbers come from?  Honestly, I
have no idea and nor do I need to care anymore when writing a new job description!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
